Eaton Farms Development Collection
© 2008 University of Connecticut
Eaton Farms Development Collection.
1959-2002.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Hamill, Hugh.
4.75 linear feet.
Materials relating to the proposed development of the Eaton farmland and related zoning disputes in Mansfield Center, CT (1987-1993).
MSS20020028
History
In 1987, local developer and attorney Paul Brody proposed to develop a piece of land in Mansfield Center, CT. The proposed development, known as "The Farms," was to consist of condominiums and office spaces. The land, located between the Mansfield Town Cemetery and Bassetts Bridge Road along Interstate 195(Storrs Road), had formerly been used as farmland, and has historical significance, since it not only borders the cemetery, but is also thought to be the location where Colonel Experience Storrs drilled troops in 1775.
A group of concerned citizens who organized themselves as the Mansfield Community Group protested the proposal, and in 1989 the project was rejected by the Planning and Zoning Commission of the Town of Mansfield. The group remained active after the rejection of what was to later be known as "Farms I," knowing that the plan would be modified and resubmitted.
"Farms II" was proposed in 1990, and the Mansfield Community Group contested the plan mainly on the basis of ecological concerns: the aquifer, Eaton Bog, and drainage issues. The plan was rejected by the Planning and Zoning Commission, and the developer contested their decision in the Rockville Superior Court. In 1993, the court upheld the Planning and Zoning Commission's decision. The Eaton land was later aquired by the town and remains undeveloped.
Date Event
1987 September "The Farms" [I] development proposed
1989 May 17 "The Farms" rejected by Planning and Zoning Commission
1990 January 23 "The Farms II" proposed
1990 June 4 "The Farms II" rejected by Planning and Zoning Commission
1990 June 25 Developer appealed Planning and Zoning Commission decision to Rockville Superior Court
1993 April 28 Court denied appeal
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials that chronicle the struggle against the proposed development of the Eaton farmland as well as the appeals to the Planning and Zoning Commission of the Town of Mansfield to make changes to the zoning regulations in order to preserve historically significant and ecologically fragile land. The collection is comprehensive in terms of covering the resistance to the proposal, but although it contains some documents related to the developer's side of the dispute, it is fairly biased towards the opposition. Also contained in this collection is significant information regarding the geological and hydrological features of the affected area of Mansfield Center.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history. See especially the records of the Connecticut Citizens Action Group (CCAG).For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as donated and is in primarily chronological order. The contents of many folders are in reverse chronological order.
Separated Material
Historic Mansfield Center. Dodd
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Places:
Mansfield Center (Conn.)
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.; Physical geology--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.; Land use--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.; Land use--Environmental aspects--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.; Zoning--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.; Real estate development--Environmental aspects--Connecticut--Mansfield Center.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Photographs.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Photocopies.; Notes.; Books.; Lawsuits.; Speeches.; Petitions.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Histories.
Occupations:
Functions:
Titles:
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection. Documents containing telephone numbers have been redacted and the originals are filed separately.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Hugh Hamill in March 2002. Additional materials were donated in September 2002.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection,1959-2002.
  - Summary, undated (Box 1:1)
  - Farms I Special Permit Application, 1987-1988 (Box 1:2-4)
  - Historic Mansfield Center, 2002 (Box 1:5)
  - Mansfield Zoning Regulations, 1982-1989 (Box 1:6)
  - Eaton Property Environmental Review Team Report, 1987 (Box 1:7)
  - Farms I Chronology, 1989 (Box 1:8-10)
  - Farms I Chronology, 1982-1988. (Box 2:11-13)
  - Water Issues, 1981-1990 (Box 2:14)
  - Water Issues: Farms II, 1989 (Box 2:15)
  - Opposition Resources, 1988-1990 (Box 2:16)
  - Opposition Consultants (Water), 1973-1993 (Box 2:17)
  - DEP & Legal Controversies, 1988-1991 (Box 2:18)
  - Farms II: Public Hearing, 1989-1990 (Box 2:19)
  - Farms II: Correspondence & Testimony, 1981-1993 (Box 2:20)
  - Farms II Chronology, 1989-1991 (Box 3:21-22)
  - Farms II: Summary in Opposition, 1990 (Box 3:23)
  - Farms II Rejected: Press, 1990 (Box 3:24)
  - Clippings & Other Resources, 1984-1994 (Box 3:25)
  - Brief of Developer's Appeal, 1992 (Box 3:26)
  - Mansfield Town Plan & Commentary, 1990-1994 (Box 3:27-28)
  - Doug Crockett Brief, 1992 (Box 4:29)
  - Rockville Court Decision, 1993 (Box 4:30)
  - Aftermath, 1990-2002 (Box 4:31)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 4:32)
  - Maps, 1959-1982 (Box 5)